Guide to the Dave Hughes Papers1970-2015
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Dave Hughes papers
1970-2015
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Hughes, Dave, 1945-
2609
Collection 2609, MtBC, us
10.5 linear feet
The Dave Hughes Papers consists primarily of author proofs, drafts, research notes, and unpublished works written by Dave Hughes. Dave Hughes is the author of over 20 books on fly fishing as well as the author of fly fishing articles published in well respected fly fishing magazines.
Dave Hughes was born in Astoria, Oregon in 1945 and graduated from the University of Oregon in 1967. He is the author of over 25 books and articles on fly fishing, fly tying, and works of fiction. His works include Western Hatches (written with Rick Hafele), Handbook of Hatches, Reading Trout Water, Wet Flies, Essential Trout Flies, Nymphs for Streams and Stillwaters, and Trout Flies. His articles have appeared in Gray's Sporting Journal, Field and Stream, Fly Fishing the West and Fly Fisherman. As of 2022 he is a regular columnist contributor for Fly Rod and Reel, and Flyfishing and Trout Journal.
Dave was founding president of Oregon Trout in 1983, awarded life membership in the Federation of Fly Fishers in 1985, the Pete Hidy honorary life membership in the FlyFishers Club of Oregon in 1992, and received the prestigious Letcher Lambuth Angler Craftsman Award in 2008 from the Washington Fly Fishing Club. He lives in Portland, Oregon with his wife, Japanese fly fishing writer Masako Tani, and their daughter Kosumo.
Most of the information above is taken from the Biography page on Dave Hughes website: http://davehughesflyfishing.com/about-dave/
The collection consists primarily of writings, drafts and final published works of the fly fishing and fly tying writer Dave Hughes. Varying levels of manuscript and magazine article drafts illustrate project progression and Hughes' writing process. Most works are non-fiction, relating to fly fishing and fly tying, but there are also some fiction works and works of poetry. The collection also includes both records of Hughe's daily life and his firsthand fly fishing experience in the form of fishing Logs and pocket journals where he has noted both environmental conditions, and the methods he and his companions used while fishing. Most of his experience is in the Rocky Mountain Region and Northwestern United States, but his writings also include fishing trips and travel in Canada, Japan, and Chile. There are both illustrated and physical examples of fly fishing lures, and other illustrative materials that were used in the production of his published works.
Collection is open to research.
Literary manuscripts, personal papers, diaries, and other materials created or collected by Dave Hughes of Portland, Oregon, were purchased from him by Montana State University in 2016. In November 2022, acession 2682 was added to the collection as boxes 17-26, and items 10 and 11 in box 16. These items were orriginally found in the Vernon E. Gallup papers (accession number 2696).
Hughes, Dave, 1945---Archives
Authors, American--20th century; Fly fishing; Fishers; Fly tyers
Fishing and Canning; Sports and Recreation; Bozeman; Montana; Environmental Conditions; Fisheries and Wildlife
Manuscripts for publication; Manuscripts; Diaries
- Description of all materials provided by donor with notes on each item (Box 14, Folder 1)
  Oregon BLM map; Collection of articles in three ring binder
- Manuscripts
  This series includes both edited drafts and final manuscripts of several of his published books. Final manuscripts in the collection are all unbound printouts of the final work, as well as some digital copies on removable media. Drafts vary from handwritten first drafts, to edited progressive drafts illustrating his editorial process. Some of the draft material includes unpublished chapters and working notes such as outlines and other writing ideas. Also included are illustrative materials such as sketches of page layouts and suggestions for illustrations.
  - Big Indian Creek (Box 1, Folder 1)
    typed drafts and Authors Proof
  - Typed draft in binder for Big Indian Creek (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Handwritten diary that is basis for book Big Indian Creek and typed version of diary (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Nymphs for Streams and Stillwaters (Box 1, Folder 2)
    typed draft pages 1-250 and Style Sheet
  - Nymphs for Streams and Stillwaters (Box 1, Folder 3)
    typed draft pages 250-579
  - Matching Mayflies (Box 1, Folder 4)
    typed first draf
  - Matching Mayflies (Box 2, Folder 1)
    typed final draft
  - Trout Flies (Box 3, Folder 1)
    draft 1-200, image plates and correspondence with publisher
  - Trout Flies (Box 3, Folder 2)
    draft 201-550
  - Trout Flies (Box 3, Folder 3)
    draft 551-884 and Index
  - Dry Fly Fishing (Box 3, Folder 4)
    typed draft and handwritten research notes
  - Dry Fly Fishing, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    typed draft
  - Dry Fly Fishing (Box 4, Folder 2)
    author proofs
  - Dry Fly Fishing (Box 4, Folder 3)
    typed draft and chapter outline notes
  - Dry Fly Fishing (Box 4, Folder 4)
    typed draft and photo script
  - An Angler's Astoria (Box 5, Folder 3)
    the unpublished chapters
  - Angler's Astoria: First Draft, Pen Draft, Includes Some Unpublished Chapters 1-4 (Box 17, Folder 1-4)
  - Angler's Astoria: Unpublished Chapters (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Angler's Astoria: Edited Manuscript Carbon 1-2 (Box 18, Folder 1-2)
  - 6 original pieces of art by Grant Linn used in An Angler's Astoria (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Western Streamside Guide, April 1997 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    revised edition draft
  - Western Streamside Guide, May 1997 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Western Streamside Guide (Box 8, Folder 5)
    revised edition notes, hatch list, author proofs
  - Western Streamside Guide (Box 10, Folder 3)
    notes and author proof
  - Western Streamside Guide (Box 10, Folder 4)
    author proof 1-66
  - Western Streamside Guide (Box 11, Folder 1)
    67-index
  - Western Streamside Guide: Edited Fist Draft, 1987 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Western Streamside Guide: Xerox of Manuscript (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Western Streamside Guide: Final Manuscript Copy (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Wet Flies (Box 8, Folder 6)
    pattern list with hand tied flies; proofs of book cover; casting diagrams; 17 photos and 2 color print fly images for book
  - Wet Flies Notebook with notes for book Wet Flies (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Wet Flies "WET-1" (Box 15, Floppy-disc 1)
  - Wet Flies "WET-2" (Box 15, Floppy-disc 2)
  - Wet Flies "WET-3" (Box 15, Floppy-disc 3)
  - Original photograph arrangement sheets for Wet Flies (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Strategies for Stillwater (Box 9, Folder 6)
    author proof
  - Strategies for Stillwater (Box 10, Folder 1)
    early typed draft
  - Strategies for Stillwater (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Strategies for Stillwater: Outline, Chapter Notes, and Unpublished Chapter (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Strategies for Stillwater: Edited First Draft 1 of 2 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Strategies for Stillwater: Edited First Draft 2 of 2 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Handbook of Hatches: Edited Final Manuscript, Returned from Stackpole Books 1-2 (Box 19, Folder 2-3)
  - Handbook of Hatches: Copy of Final Book (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Reading Trout Water: First Draft (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Reading Trout Water: Final Manuscript-Copy 1-2 (Box 19, Folder 6-7)
  - Reading Water, Finding Fish: Edited Final Manuscript, Author's Corrections (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
  - Tactics for Trout: Working Notes and Chapter Outlines (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Tactics for Trout: Edited First Draft 1-3 (Box 20, Folder 4-6)
  - Tactics for Trout: Final Manuscript-Copy 1-2 (Box 21, Folder 1-2)
  - Tackle and Technique for Taking Trout: Edited First Draft 1-2, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 3-4)
  - Tackle and Technique: Final Draft, Photo Captions, Illustration Captions, Xerox of Illustrations 1-2 (Box 21, Folder 5-6)
  - Tackle and Technique: Author's Original Manuscript 1 of 2 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Tackle and Technique: Author's Original Manuscript 2 of 2 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Western Angler's Entomology, AKA Western Hatches: Copy of Edited Second Draft 1-3 (Box 22, Folder 2-4)
  - Western Hatches: Second Draft and Pictures-Yellow Copy 1-3 (Box 22, Folder 5-7)
  - Western Hatches: Original Manuscript: Includes Carbons of Indexes 1-3 (Box 23, Folder 1-3)
  - Fly Fishing Basics: Edited First Draft 1-3 (Box 23, Folder 4-6)
  - Yellowstone River: First Draft and Xerox 1-2 (Box 24, Folder 1-2)
  - Yellowstone River: Original Manuscript (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - American Fly Tying Manual: Edited First Draft (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - American Fly Tying Manual: Working Notebook (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - American Fly Tying Manual: Materials For Plates (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - American Fly Tying Manual: Copy of Final Manuscript (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Fly Fishing Magazine: Western Fly Fishing Guide: Final Manuscript Copy 1-2 (Box 24, Folder 8-9)
  - Unpublished manuscript with notes, Western Caddis Hatches by Hafele and Hughes (Box 16, Item 1)
  - Unpublished manuscript with notes, Western Caddis Hatches by Hafele and Hughes (Box 16, Compact-disc 1)
    Item is located in a pocket inside Item #1 in Box 16
  - Unpublished manuscript with notes, Western Caddis Hatches by Hafele and Hughes (Box 16, Floppy-disc 1)
  - Unpublished manuscript with notes, Western Stonefly Hatches by Hafele and Hughes (Box 16, Item 2)
  - Unpublished manuscript with notes, Western Stonefly Hatches by Hafele and Hughes (Box 16, Compact-disc 2)
    Item is located in a pocket inside Item #2 in Box 16
  - Unpublished manuscript with notes, Western Stonefly Hatches by Hafele and Hughes (Box 16, Floppy-disc 2)
- Other Writings
  These materials encapsulate writings that did not result in a book publication. These writings further illustrate and preserve Hughes' writing process and the collaborative process of contributing to popular publications.
  - Summer of Grass, Summer of Wood, Home River (Box 2, Folder 2)
    handwritten draft
  - Small Stream, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    final typed draft
  - The Killer Boys (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Hermaphrodites to Dries (Box 4, Folder 5)
    typed draft published in anthology City Fishing
  - Kept Man, Life Cycles, Love Story of the Trout (Box 4, Folder 6)
    typed drafts published in Fly, Rod and Reel
  - When to go to Narragansett, Shagging, The Best Fly Fishing he ever had, Trilobite (Box 4, Folder 7)
    typed drafts unpublished
  - Death of a Trout Stream (Box 4, Folder 8)
    notes, draft, and timeline published in An Anglers Astoria
  - What It Was (draft published in Love Story of the Trout) and Widowmaker (Box 4, Folder 9)
    published in Big Sky Journal
  - Published and unpublished poetry (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Unpublished short fiction and essays (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Fishing for Memorable Moments, Roof Hunter, Tied to the Tides, Things That Go Thump in the Lake
  - Time and the River (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Time and the River (Box 5, Folder 5)
    notes, chapter outlines, and handwritten draft
  - Time and the River (Box 5, Folder 6)
    note cards and editor correspondence
  - Time and the River (Box 5, Folder 7)
    typed draft pages 1-250
  - Time and the River (Box 6, Folder 1)
    typed draft pages 251-494
  - Time and the River (Box 6, Folder 2)
    typed draft parts 1 and 2 with several handwritten note pages/cards
  - Time and the River (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Time and the River (Box 6, Folder 4)
    typed draft pages 1-278
  - Time and the River (Box 7, Folder 1)
    typed draft pages 279-494
  - Subsurface Fly Fishing and Flies (Box 7, Folder 2)
    typed draft (Wet Flies)
  - Subsurface Fly Fishing and Flies (Box 7, Folder 3)
    typed draft (Wet Flies) and reading list
  - Subsurface Fly Fishing and Flies (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Sly Nemes handtied flies (Box 8, Folder 2)
    6 total and thank you card to Dave, typed draft of Soft hackled flies, and unbound authors copy
  - Basic Trout Flies (Box 9, Folder 2)
    draft and photo list
  - Fly Fishing...and tying typed booklets (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - The True Importance of Polly Rosborough in Santiam Hatch (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Workshop booklets: Nymphs for Streams and Stillwaters. 16 pages; Matching Hatches Simplified. 16 pages; Tying Trout Stream Nymphs. 16 pages; Small Stream Trout Flies:Ten Deadlies. 8 pages; Small Stream Trout Flies: A deadly dozen. 8 pages
  - 7 versions of Entomology and the Artificial Fly by Rick Hafele and Dave Hughes (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 4 Chile trip notebooks, January 24-February 9, 1995; February 9-February 15, 1995; January 9-January 27, 1996; January 28-February 14, 1996 (Box 11, Item 1-4)
  - Index of magazine articles, 1978-1994 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Magazine articles Salmon, Trout Steelheader (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Magazine articles Flyfishing (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Magazine articles Fly Fisherman (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Magazine articles Fly Fishing the West (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Magazine articles The Flyfisher (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Magazine articles American Angler and Fly Tyer (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Magazine articles Field and Stream (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Magazine articles Scientific Angler (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Magazine articles Fishing the North Country (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Magazine articles Western Outdoors (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Magazine articles Northwest Living (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Magazine articles Outdoor Life (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Magazine articles Game Journal (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Magazine articles Saltwater Sportsman (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Magazine articles Fins and Feathers (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Magazine articles California Angler (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Magazine articles Flyfishing News (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Magazine articles Oregonian Northwest (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Magazine articles Entomology Journal (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Magazine articles Flytying (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Tear sheets various periodicals (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper clipping various papers (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Articles in angling club newsletters (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Article Drafts Exchanged Between Hughes and Gallup 1-2 (Box 25, Folder 1-2)
  - Upper Yellowstone Forgotten Fishing: Longhand, Summer 1991 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Article Drafts and Correspondence, Field and Stream 1-2, 1990-1992 (Box 25, Folder 4-5)
  - Article Drafts and Correspondence, Fly Fishing Magazine, 1990-1991 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Article Drafts and Correspondence, Fly Fisherman, 1990 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Article Drafts and Correspondence, American Angler, 1991 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Article Draft, Game Journal (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Article Draft, Rod and Reel, 1990 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Article Draft, Salmon, Trout Steelheader, 1992 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Article Draft, Game Country, 1991 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Various Magazine First Drafts: Includes Fiction Drafts that Might Become a Book 1-2, 1992-1993 (Box 26, Folder 5-6)
- Fishing Logs
  Throughout his fishing career Dave Hughes took detailed notes on his outings and trips. His fishing logs are formatted templates that record: Date, Time, Stream/Lake, Section (of lake/stream), Who (was in attendance), Transportation, Weather, Weather Temperature, Water Conditions, Water Temperature, Natural, Time, Imitation, Methods, Fish, and Notes. Included within the pages and binders are other materials related to his experience like receipts, fishing licenses, fishing regulations, event and guide service fliers, sketches of the flies used, maps and directions to fishing locations, and "book of lists" which are organized checklists of items he needed for camping, fishing, boating, and hunting. Some physical fishing flies are also included.
  CAUTION ADVISED: the notebooks in this series include fishing flies/lures attached to pages throughout the documents. Fishing flies have sharp hooks which can pierce, stab or cut exposed skin. Please exercise caution to limit the chance of injury, and/or the chance of items becoming dislodged from their proper location.
  - Fishing log, 1974-1977 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Fishing log, 1975-1976 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Fishing log, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Fishing log, 1979-1982 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - 1987, 1988; 1989; 1990; 1991 (Box 16, Item 3)
  - 1990, 1991; 1992 (Box 16, Item 4)
  - 1992, 1993; 1994 (Box 16, Item 5)
  - 1996, 1997; 1998 (Box 16, Item 6)
  - 1999, 2000; 2001 (Box 16, Item 7)
  - 2002, 2003; 2004 (Box 16, Item 8)
  - 2005, 2006; 2007; 2008; 2009; 2010 (Box 16, Item 9)
- Pocket Journals
  Dave Hughes kept pocket size journals for use taking notes in the moment. Many of the notes on water conditions and fishing lures used may have been transcribed later into his fishing logs, and other notes included are comprised of names and addresses for various people, trip experiences, writing ideas and notes such as lines of poetry, checklists and brief reminders. Most of the titles and dates are taken either from the titles provided by Hughes or from the dates included within the notebooks. Physical fishing flies have also been attached to pages within the notebooks.
  - Oregon, Arizona, Utah, 1988 (Box 15, Item 4)
  - May 1988 (Box 15, Item 5)
  - December 1988 (Box 15, Item 6)
  - May 1989 (Box 15, Item 7)
  - January 1, 1989-September 1, 1989 (Box 15, Item 8)
  - December 1989 (Box 15, Item 9)
  - 1990 (Box 15, Item 10)
  - Sierra, 1990 (Box 15, Item 11)
  - Yellowstone, 1991 (Box 15, Item 12-13)
  - July 1992 (Box 15, Item 14)
  - Japan, 1992 (Box 15, Item 15)
  - Wisconsin, 1994 (Box 15, Item 16)
  - September 10, 1994 (Box 15, Item 17)
  - May 12, 1995 (Box 15, Item 18)
  - July 25, 1995 (Box 15, Item 19)
  - 1995 (Box 15, Item 20)
  - June 1996 (Box 15, Item 45)
  - July 1996 (Box 15, Item 46)
  - September 6, 1996 (Box 15, Item 21)
  - Chile, 1996 (Box 15, Item 22)
  - 1997 (Box 15, Item 23-24)
  - April 29, 1998 (Box 15, Item 25)
  - October 21, 1998 (Box 15, Item 26)
  - April 1, 1999 (Box 15, Item 27)
  - July 27, 1999 (Box 15, Item 28)
  - Japan, 1999 (Box 15, Item 29)
  - May 2001 (Box 15, Item 47)
  - December 16, 2001 (Box 15, Item 30)
  - March 5, 2002 (Box 15, Item 31)
  - March 27, 2002 (Box 15, Item 32)
  - June 18, 2002 (Box 15, Item 33)
  - January 19, 2003 (Box 15, Item 34)
  - August 9, 2004 (Box 15, Item 35)
  - January 1-December 31, 2006 (Box 15, Item 36)
  - December 11, 2006 (Box 15, Item 37)
  - July 6, 2007 (Box 15, Item 38)
  - July 23, 2007 (Box 15, Item 39)
  - April 2012 (Box 15, Item 40)
  - November 2012 (Box 15, Item 41)
  - Lochsa River, September 2013 (Box 15, Item 42)
  - 2013-2014 (Box 15, Item 43)
  - 2014 (Box 15, Item 44)
- Untitled Sketch (Box 16, Item 10)
- Matted Photo, Isoynchia Salderi, Mahogany Dun, Male Dun (subimago), Yellow Breeches, By Eugene P Macrel, circa 1986 (Box 16, Item 11)
- Dave Hughes web archive